<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certain additions to the booke of gunnery, with a supply of fire-workes all done by the former author Thomas Smith ... ; both pleasant and profitable.</title>
            <author>Smith, Thomas, fl. 1600-1627.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B15851</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24490778</idno>
  <idno type="VID">178591</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264224810</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 22855.5_pt2</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S116364</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B15851)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178591)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1824:28b)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certain additions to the booke of gunnery, with a supply of fire-workes all done by the former author Thomas Smith ... ; both pleasant and profitable.</title>
                  <author>Smith, Thomas, fl. 1600-1627.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>76 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H.L. and are to be sold by R. Dawlman, in Fleet-street neere the great Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁴ K².</note>
                  <note>Pages 68, 69, and 72 misnumbered as 72, 73, and 76 respectively.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: has print show-through and is torn, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge) Library.</note>
                  <note>With: The art of gunnery ... / compiled by Thomas Smith. London  : Printed for William Ponsonby, 1600 (identified as STC 22855+ and as STC 22855.5).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Gunnery --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Artillery --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Ordnance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:178591:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:178591:1"/>
            <p>CERTAIN ADDITIONS TO THE BOOKE OF GVNNERY, with a sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of <hi>Fire-Workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All done by the former Author <hi>Thomas Smith</hi> Souldier of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke vpon Tweede.</p>
            <p>Both pleasant and profitable.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device? (not found in McKerrow): wheat sheaf supported by two animals, below which is the motto Cor unum via una, all surrounded by decorative scrolls. (Compare devices in STC 13799 and 2390.5.)</figDesc>
               <q>COR VNVM VIA VNA</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. L.</hi> and are to be sold by <hi>R. Dawlman,</hi> in Fleet-street neere the great Conduit. 1627.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:178591:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:178591:2"/>
            <head>CERTAINE PRINCIPALL points belonging to the Art of GVNNERIE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Reade in <hi>Tartaglia</hi> of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that shall make no noyse being fired out of any peece of great Ordnance, where he saith it is not lawfull to be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, neither to shew the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it. But I am assured he neuer burnt any of it: for he doth confesse in his Epistle to his booke, that hee neuer shot in any Peece. Also I haue heard it confidently affirmed, that there is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible powder (of a white colour as they say) the which being fired out of any peece of Ordnance, the peece hauing had her due loading therof, it shal make no rore, crack or report (as we terme it): but I neither beleeue the one nor the other. For I say it is impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make Powder that shall burne and haue anie force, but that the flame therof being resolued into a windy substance, enclosed within the concaue of the Peece, violently thrusting it selfe out of the Peece in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the open ayre, must of necessity giue a rore or crack, more or lesse, in proportion to that ayrie sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance so fired, &amp; compacted within the Peece: many examples I could alledge for further proofe hereof.</p>
            <p>The vertue &amp; force of gun-powder consists in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:178591:3"/> Saltpeter, for the brimstone &amp; the cole is but onely to maintaine the flame therof: for the brimstone it selfe is apt to flame with any sparkle, and once flamed, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the matter or Saltpeter to flame. The cole is apt to kindle or burne with any sparkle, but not to flame, yet maintaineth the flame of the other two materials. The best Matter is that which is refined without any fatnesse. The best brimstone is that which hath no drosse in it. And the best cole are those that are made of the softest &amp; lightest wood. These three materials being pounded very fine, &amp; their true proportioned parts mixed &amp; wrought accordingly by such as haue skill in the art, makes perfect good powder: they vse wherof was neuer better known than in these present dayes. The goodnesse of any powder may be known by the colour, by the taste of the tongue, and by the burning; and a man may make as much and as little thereof at a time as he pleaseth, hauing prouision of furniture for that purpose.</p>
            <p>Any Peece discharged diuerse times with moyst powder, will sooner heate, than being discharged the like number of times with like quantitie of fine dry powder: for the moist powder is longer in burning, &amp; causeth the peece to work lesse effect than if it had beene charged with like quantity of dry powder.</p>
            <p>If you haue by experience found that your powder is not forcible, the neerest way to strēgthen the same is, by putting to euerie pound thereof one ounce of refined Matter finely pounded, and then moistening the same with vineger, or rather the water of Saltpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; beating the same in a morter of other vessell as finely as you can, with a wooden pestell (for it is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:178591:3"/> to beat the same with any iron toole for fear of a sparke) &amp; sifting the same thorow a verie fine sieue, corning &amp; drying the same, it will be of more force a great deale than it was at the first time. Som do make excellent good corne powder, so fine, that the cornes thereof are like Thime seed.</p>
            <p>I haue read &amp; heard some of that opinion, that if a little quicke-siluer bee put in amongst the powder where with any peece is loaden, &amp; a close wad there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, that that peece shall giue a greater report than if she had beene charged with the same like quantity of powder and wad, and wanting the quicke-siluer, the which I did experiment in a Calliuer but could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue no such matter.</p>
            <p>If you would outshoot any other man in any one peece of Ordnance, the peece to be loaden at eyther time with one like quantity of one like powder, wad &amp; bullet, &amp; discharged at one like randon; then after you haue loaden the peece with her due of powder, put the same closely home with the end of your ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer staffe, &amp; after make a roūd wad as hard &amp; close as you are able to thrust home to the powder, and put your bullet close home to the said wad, but put no wad after it, if the marke lye, sons the peece mouth be any whit eleuated; otherwise put in a little wad after the bullet, to keepe the bullet close to the wad in his right place. Also if you take strong canuas soaked in oyle, &amp; sow the some close &amp; round about the bullet, that the bullet may fill the hollow cilinder of the peece, &amp; put the same close home, as afore, that bullet will range further than being discharged hauing a lesse wad, &amp; being vncoated. <hi>Tartalia</hi> affirms, that the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:178591:4"/> powder put into the peece and rammed home to the breech, being bored thorow with a staffe of an inch or ¾ in thicknesse, to the breech of the peece, &amp; after a close wad put home to the said powder, &amp; the bullet put home after it, that that bullet shall range more ground than it would haue done if the powder in the peece had not been bored thorow, as is aboue said.</p>
            <p>Any peece being charged with very dry powder, that is hard corned, shall not fire all the powder, but a great many of these cornes will passe out of the peece vnburnt when the peece is recharged, as you may by experience proue out of a Musket or Calliuer: and the closer that the wad is made that is put into the peece after the powder, it wil cause more of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to fire, than hauing a lesser wad.</p>
            <p>Any peece of Ordnance although the same be loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with verie good and dry powder, if the peece lye long loaden, the powder will grow moist, by reason the Saltpeter will work and grow dankish within the chamber of the peece where the powder lyeth: &amp; if the said peter be not well refined, it will sooner grow dankish than that which hath been well refined: also the same will grow moist sooner in the winter than in the summer, &amp; sooner on the sea than on the land. Two peeces in all respects equall saue length, at point blank, or at any degree of the randon, discharg'd with one like bullet and quantity of powder, the longer peece will still outshoore the shorter: but giuing the shorter peece a more quantitie of powder than the longer, the shorter peece will outshoot the longer.</p>
            <p>A Musket that shooteth ⅔ parts or ¾ in powder of the bullet weight that is fit for the said Musket, will
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:178591:4"/> range further &amp; pierce deeper than a Calliuer that is recharged with a fit bullet and ⅔ or ¾ parts of his bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets weight: but in giuing to eyther peece a like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of powder, I meane giuing the Musket but ⅔ parts in powder of the weight of the Calliuers bullet, then shall the Calliuer do more execution, and range further than the Musket. And in like case a Fawcon or Saker being discharged with the whole weight of powder of the bullet fit for the said peece, shall doe more execution and range further than a Canon or Culuering that shooteth a fit bullet, and hath but the like quantitie of powder that the lesser peece hath.</p>
            <p>Any peece of Ordnance that is presently recharged after her loading, or that hath not lien long loaden, will conuey her bullet more ground, &amp; do more exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, than letting the same peece lye long loaden, the piece discharged at eyther time at one like degree of randon, and with oae like quantity of one like powder, wad and bullet.</p>
            <p>Two peeces in all respects equal, both loaden alike with one like powder, and laid at the marke from one like platform, the center of the marke iust point blank with the center of the hollow cilinder of the peece, and within the leuel range of both peeces, the one of the said peeces brought to the marke with her true disparture, and the other peece with her mettals, that peece so disparted shal strike the marke, and the other peece shall shoot ouer the marke.</p>
            <p>A bullet of any mettal discharged out of any peece of Ordnance, by how much more violent or swifter it is driuen thorow the ayre, it is in proportiō to that violent mouing so much the lighter, and the more
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:178591:5"/> lighter, the more easie is the passage thereof; and the more forcibly it flyeth, the more force it worketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst any resisting obiect, and flyeth in a staighter line in his swift motion, than in his decreasing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. And by how much the swiftnesse thereof de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaseth, in like proportion to that mouing doeth it grow heauier and declineth.</p>
            <p>A bullet of iron or any other mettall that is not so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidly cast, but hath in it som little hole or empty place, being discharged out of any peece of great Ordnance doth fly thorow the aire with a more whistling sound than if the same had been perfectly solid and round cast. And any bullet recharged from any peece of Ordnance, wil make a greater sound passing violently thorow the ayre, at the first shot, than at the second, third, or fourth shot, being recharged one presently after another, by reason the ayre at the first shot was quiet, close, and vndiuided, and therefore of force must resist the passage of the bullet, more than when the same is moued or diuided.</p>
            <p>The violent motion of a bullet discharged out of a Cannon or Culuering, or other such like great peece of Ordnance, passeth with such a strong motion, and driueth the aire before it in the passage of range ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that flying ouer houses three or foure hundred yards aboue the same, doth often shake them in such sort, that the glasse on the windows will break in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; the platters on the benches, or such like things standing loose, will fall down▪ &amp; the higher that such houses are that are so vnder the passage or range of the bullet, are more subiect to the hurt or shake therof than lower houses which are neere to the peece, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:178591:5"/> vnder the like range of the bullet; w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> is a strange thing, that the motion of the ayre driuen &amp; driuing the bullet, should haue such a power to shake or hurt a great obiect rather than a lesser, both standing vnder the like passage of the bullet. Also it hath more power to hurt an obiect standing firme (tho further from the peece) than a moue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able obiect, as a man or beast, being much neerer to the peece, &amp; both vnder the range or passage of the bullet.</p>
            <p>Any Peece being discharged with her due loading in powder &amp; wad, with a fit bullet of yrō, &amp; after being dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with the like quantitie of like powder &amp; wad, &amp; with a bullet of lead of like diameter to the yron bullet, shal make seueral ranges, thogh the peece be discharged at one like grade, the bullet of iron shal outsly the bullet of lead; but loding the peece with her due of pouder, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the weight of the yron bullet, &amp; after loding her with the same pouder, giuing her the like proportion to the weight of the leaden bullet, the range of the leadē bullet shal extēd furder than the range of the iron bullet</p>
            <p>Two peeces of like bore, but contrary length, hauing one like loading, and laid at one like degree of the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant, to shoot at any one marke, without the leuel range of each peece, but within the best randō of both peeces, shal make like ranges: but if the said peece haue one like visual sight (to wit) if they haue both one like length gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them by an inch rule to reach the said marke (which some Gunners call the rule of flat) the ranges of those 2 peeces shall greatly differ, &amp; though they haue both one like lēgth giuē thē by the said rule to reach the mark yet shall they alter by the degrees of the quadrant, the shor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter peece shal be eleuated at a higher point than the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, &amp; therfore of force must range furder than the lōger</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:178591:6"/>
            <p>It is a common opinion amongst a great many Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that any peece of Ordnance lyeth point blank that is truely brought to the marke, whether the said Marke be ascending or descending, the peece laid truely against the said Marke without any length giuen to reach it: but I say, that there is but one precise point blanke, that is, when the peece is so laid that the line issuing from the centre of the hollow cilinder of the peece cutteth the centre of the marke; and if it were or might bee exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded forth right, would cut directly the true horizon: or a point blanke or leuell line is that which by suppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on extendeth it selfe from the centre of the peece tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the centre of the marke vnto the true horizon, for there can be but one precise streight line or point blank, as the Gunners tearme it, which must be that visuall or supposed line, whose ends are both of equall height. Or a direct straight line is that which when a perpendicular line falleth thereon, diuideth it into equall angles, as is taught in Ewclid and other bookes of Geometry. The easiest and truest way to know when your peece lyeth point blanke, is by putting your rule into the peece mouth, hauing a Gunners quadrant or square thereon, and coyning your peece so, that the plummet may cut or fall on the line that makes the right angle from the centre where it hangs (called the leuell line) that peece then lyeth point blanke: all other lines visuall being extended to any marke that is eyther higher or lower than the eye, are not to be termed streight lines.</p>
            <p>If the marke which you are to shoot at be in a streight line with the concaue of the peece, and not without the point blanke or leuell range of the peece, it is an easie matter to strike diuerse markes standing in the said line,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:178591:6"/> by making the visuall line so much lower, as is betweene the true visuall line and the center of the cilinder of the peece, being the line in which the bullet flieth: &amp; if the marke be far without point blanke, it is possible to strike two markes standing in the visuall line, both in the place where the bullet first cutteth the said visuall line, and so rangeth aboue it into the ayre in his straight motion (which will not be farre from the peece) &amp; in that place where the bullet in the end of his range declining, cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the said visuall line againe in his crooked or ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding motion, which must of necessitie be eyther at or very neere to the marke.</p>
            <p>If the marke you meane to shoot at be not far without the leuell range of the peece, and something higher than point blanke, then must you so lay the peece, that the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suall lyne aymed by the superficies of the mettals of the peece (not disparting the said peece) may cut the mark: and if at the first shot the bullet light short or ouer, you may easily amend the second by adding or abating the length giuen; but if the marke be vnder point blank, and not far without the leuell range of the peece, then set vp your disparture in the mids of the superficies of the met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall at the mouth of the peece, and working as is said by experimenting one shot, it is an easie matter to make a perfect shot the second time: &amp; if you shoot at the said marke not disparting your peece, then must you lay the peece short of the mark, that the visual line passing by the metals of the peece touch a prety distāce vnder the mark</p>
            <p>All marks or obiects distant frō your peece which you are to shoot at, are in a threefold proportion to be consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of; as either the same is iust point blanke, which is in one respect only to be considered of, or it is higher
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:178591:7"/> or lower than point blanke, which is to be considered of in diuers respects, according to the distance and number of degrees the same is at, eyther in ascent or descent.</p>
            <p>Any two or mo peeces of like or contrary proportion at point blanke discharged, euery peece hauing her due loading with powder, &amp; with a bullet fit for each peece, &amp; the leuel ranges of the said peeces noted, that of those peeces whose leuell range is furthest, will still out shoot the other at any grade of the randon, giuing to euerie of the said peeces, the self like loading in powder &amp; bullet.</p>
            <p>Any two peeces differing in proportion, &amp; the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of their leuell ranges known, may so be loaden, as they shall both range one like distance of ground at one like randon: and the vtmost range of any peece knowne at any degree of randon, by abating the proportion of her powder, it is possible in two or three shoots, to shoot any part of the same randon that you will assigne.</p>
            <p>Two peeces in all respects equall saue length, moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one like degree of randon, and loaden with one like weight in contrary powder, and with one like bullet, that peece that is loaden with the best powder, will still out-range the other, although that other be the longer: but if there be but little difference betwixt the force of the powders, this proportion will not hold at euerie grade of the randon.</p>
            <p>To charge any peece of Ordnance Gunner-like, set your boudge or barrell on the wind hand of the peece, &amp; causing one of your assistants to hold the same aslope, thrust your ladle into the same, filling it full of powder, causing your fellow that holds the boudge to strike the same with a ruler; two of those ladles is the common charge of that peece. And fixing your thomb iust vnder
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:178591:7"/> the staffe of the ladle, thrust the same home to the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the peece where the powder lyeth, turning the ladle so as your thomb be directly aboue the staffe, and in so doing, the powder will fall or turn out of the Iadle cleanly; then drawing out the said ladle with the rampi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the other end of the staffe, thrust home the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with 2. or 3. strokes, causing your assistant to hold his thomb close on the touch-hole of the peece, then taking a close round wad of hay, tow, vntwisted rope, or such like, thrust in the same with your rammer-staffe close to the pouder; &amp; after put in the bullet close to the wad: &amp; if your peece be eleuated at any degree of the randon to reach the mark, it is needlesse to put in any wad after the bullet, for it will rather hinder than helpe the same: but if the peece mouth be any whit embased, then it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth to put in a wad close to the bullet, to holde the bullet in his right place: &amp; the speciall point belonging to a Gunner in charging of any great peece, is to loade the same standing sidewise of the peece, and not directly before her mouth; for it sometimes happeneth, that a peece hauing flawes or hony-combs within her, being often discharged together, doth for a season keepe some sparkes of fire in the said holes, so that thrusting home the ladle with the powder, to loade the peece standing directly before the mouth of the peece, it taketh fire and killeth the Gunner and such as are directly before the mouth of the peece, as happened in Anno 1573. at the siege of Edenborough Castle, to two experienced Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, who if they had stood sidewise to the peece, might haue escaped that danger.</p>
            <p>If you charge your peece with a cartredge, &amp; hauing put the same home to the breech, with the end of your
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:178591:8"/> rammer staffe, put after the same a good wad, and after that the bullet, as afore is taught, not forgetting to thrust the case of the cartredge thorow with your priming yron in the touch-hole of the peece, that the priming powder may be sure to take hold and to fire the same. Some vse to put a Tampion of wood in next to the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tredge, and then the bullet and wad; and some vse to cut that part of the cartredge away that lyeth next to the touch-hole: but howsoeuer you cut the same in charging any peece with a cartredge, it behoueth you to prime the cartredge through with a skrewed or wrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed priming yron made sharpe at the end, and then put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in your priming powder, you shall be sure not to faile of your purpose.</p>
            <p>In giuing fire to any great peece of Ordnance, as Cannon, Culuering, or such like, it is requisite that the Gunner thereto appointed, first see that the peece be well primed, laying a little powder about the touch-hole as a traine, and then to be nimble in giuing fire, which as soone as hee espyeth to flame, hee ought with quicknesse to retire back three or foure yards out of the danger of the reuerse of the wheeles and carriage of the peece: for oftentimes it happeneth that the wheele or axel-tree doth breake, and spoyle the Gunner that giueth fire, not hauing agilitie to moue himselfe from the danger of the same: yea, I did see a Gunner slaine with the reuerse of the wheele of a Culuering, which crushed his leg and thigh in peeces, who if hee had had a care, and nimblenesse withall, might haue escaped that misfortune. Also if the priming powder bee dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kish, or the cole of the match not cleere, the Gunner cannot speedily giue fire, and therefore behoueth to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:178591:8"/> foresee it: or if he hold the lintstocke in which his fired match is tyed, long ouer the touch-hole, the violence of the flame issuing thereout is able to spoyle him, or some thereabout, by throwing the lintstocke or staffe which he giues fire with out of his hand. I haue seene the lint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stock and match blowne out of the Gunners hand more than fourescore yards from the peece, by the violent blast of the fire issuing out at the touch-hole of the peece, in giuing fire to the same. And it is to be noted, that the wider the touch-hole of the peece is, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter flame doth issue out thereat, which causeth the peece to worke lesse effect than shee would, hauing a lesser touch-hole.</p>
            <p>Any peece of Ordnance truely disparted, shooting at any mark in a streight line from the centre of the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low concaue of the peece, and within point blanke, shall strike so much vnder the centre of the said marke (being laid iust against the midst of the said marke) as the visual distance is from the top of the said disparture to the concaue or cilinder of the peece.</p>
            <p>To make a perfect shot at any marke, whether the same be at point blanke, or at any degree ascending or descending, coyne your peece so that the centre of your eye in ayming lye close to the superficies of the middle part of the mettall at the breech: and if the marke be at point blanke, and the peece truely disparted, and the visuall line so aymed (passing by the top of the said dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture) cut the centre of the marke, then shall the bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let light so much vnder the centre of the marke as is betweene the concaue of the peece and the top of the disparture, if the winde alter not the bullet in his moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And if the marke bee further than the peece will
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:178591:9"/> reach with her mettals, then must you eleuate the peece mouth so many degrees as will reach the same, first laying the peece straight against the said Marke: and whether the marke be point blanke, aboue point blanke, or vnder point blanke, if you fixe your eye in ayming aboue the leuell sight at the breech, the visual line passing by the extreme or top of the leuell sight at the mouth of the peece, will cut vnder the mark, and will cut or diuide the supposed line in which the bullet flyeth before it come to the marke; which bullet will light aboue the marke: or fixing your eye lower than you ought at the breech, the visual line extending it selfe, will cut aboue the marke, and neuer touch the line in which the bullet flyeth.</p>
            <p>Any peece of Ordnance made hote with often shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, being cooled with water, or vineger, or other li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, and presently after recharged againe, will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey the bullet so farre, as suffering the mettall to coole of it self. And any peece discharged diuerse times &amp; not sponged and cleansed, the said peece will not doe such effect as being sponged euery time presently after she is discharged.</p>
            <p>If the Trunions of any great peece of Ordnance, as Cannon or Culuering, be placed too neere the mouth, then the peece will be so weightie at the breech, that shee will require the ayde of two or three Gunners to raise vp the same with leauers, that she may be brought to her marke; therefore to raise the same with one mans strength, so farre as another may coyne the peece to shoote at any marke assigned, lay some small coyne or peece of timber cut wedgwise, on the side of the stocke or carriage of the peece, that may reach in height with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:178591:9"/> 2. or 3. inches of the lowest part of the mettall of the breech of the peece, and putting in your leauer or hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spike as neare the end of the breech as you can, between the said peece of timber &amp; the mettall of the peece, you may raise the peece at your pleasure, so as another may coyne the same to lay her to any marke assigned: &amp; the longer your leauer is, and the least part of the end ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of that you put vnder the peece, the more weight a great deale you shall raise vp. Also by thrusting a strong leuer into the mouth of the peece, weighing the same downe at the furthest end thereof, you shall weigh or raise vp a great weight; and the longer the leauer is, the more weight shall you counterpoise.</p>
            <p>If being in seruice, you are like to leese your Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and would rather breake or burst the same in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces than the enemie should haue aduantage thereof, you may easily burst any peece with her common charge of powder, or with lesse powder than her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon charge, as thus: after you haue put home your powder, make a close wadde as hard as euer you can thrust in after the same, and then take an iron bullet half an inch or more lower than the diameter of the concaue of the peece, and put the same home close to the sayd wad, and vnder the said bullet driue in a wedge or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per peece of iron of fourteene or sixteene inches in length, made smooth and small at the one end, and great at the other, almost the height of the bullet, and giuing fire with a traine, the bullet will runne vpon the same wedge, and hauing no passage by reason the sayd wedge doth stop the way thereof, the peece perforce must breake in peeces: or you may burst any peece with her cōmon charge in pouder at any part thereof, in thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:178591:10"/> her mouth into water to that part you would haue broken, &amp; giuing fire by some traine, the peece wil burst at that part without the superficies of the water. The like may be done as some hold opinion in thrusting the peece mouth into a hole made three or foure foot deep into the earth, ramming the earth close about the same, so as no ayre may passe out at the peece mouth: or lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the peece vpon the ground vpon some pieces of timber laid vnder the forepart and hinder part thereof, and making a hollow place vnder the mids thereof, make therein a good fire, and with a paire of bellowes make the peece thorough hote, and with a sledge or great hammer striking the peece in the mids, the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle part of the peece lying hollow, you may easily break the same.</p>
            <p>If you would foretell whether any peece of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance will shoote short or ouer anie marke appointed, standing on any side of and from the same peece, and not beholding the visuall line how the peece is layd to the marke, by hauing tried and seene the fall of the bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, the first shot is an easie matter to shew whether the said peece shall shoot short or ouer any other time, being loaden euery time alike (as thus:) before the peece bee discharged the first time, set vp a Iaueling, Halbard, or anie streight staffe, directly before the mouth of the peece, and on the same make a priuie marke hard by the vpper or highest part of the mettall, and when the peece is brought to the same platforme againe, and laid to her marke, and hath her length giuen her to reach the mark, before the Gunner giue fire, set vp the staffe againe in the same place, or cause another to set the same vp, and if the highest part of the mettall at the peece mouth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:178591:10"/> be eleuate aboue the said marke on the staffe (which you may espy a prettie distance from the peece) then the said peece will out-shoot the first shot: but if the vpper part of the mettall at the mouth be vnder the said marke on the staffe, then the peece will shoot short of the other short, being loaden with one like quantitie of powder and bullet.</p>
            <p>If you would annoy the enemie, and can come to serue vnder them without suspicion, and would poison their Ordnance, or anie peece thereof, so as the same should not readily be made to shoot, watch a fit time, and poure a little hote oyle thorough a small tunnell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the touch-hole of the peece, the peece mouth a little imbased; or raising her mouth a little, powre in a little water or other liquor thereat, the which will soake thorow the wad into the powder, so as the same will not fire, or else cloying vp the touch-hole with nayles dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the head, you may for a season hinder the same from shooting, to the great anoyance of the enemy, and furtherance of your friends, they hauing some priuie warning thereof: the chiefe and readiest way if a peece be poisoned, is, to draw the same, or if the touch-hole be cloyed vp, is to make a traine in at the peece mouth to the chamber where her loading lyeth, and so rechar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging her, it will blow out the same, or else it must per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force be drilled out.</p>
            <p>The Platforme whereon your Ordnance is planted in seruice, ought to bee stored with strong woodden plankes of timber, or paued with broad smooth stones, layed close together, no higher in one place than in another, but flat and plaine on the superficies thereof, for the wheeles and carriage to make their reuers vpon:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:178591:11"/> for if the platforme bee not made, the wheeles in often reuersing will so sinke into the ground, that the peeces without great trouble and more strength of men, will not be brought to their right platforme againe; especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally after moist weather, the ground being wet before: and the peece shall sometimes shoot amisse, by reason the one wheele will sometimes sinke deeper than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The platforme behinde the carriage would bee made a little higher than before; so shall the Gunners with more ease a great deale bring the peece to her true platforme after she is reuersed.</p>
            <p>If you would see whether the peece you are to serue with be cleane without flawes, hony combs, or crackes, then turning her mouth towards the sun, being vnloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, with a looking-glasse you may cast the beame of the sunne into the concaue of the peece: or if the funne doe not shine, with a lighted candle put on the end of a clouen stick you may also see the same: but if you feare that shee hath some cracke, blow her with a quarter or halfe of her loading in powder, and presently stop her mouth with some cloth or other thing, that no smoake issue out, causing another to doe the like at the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hole: and if there be any crack in the peece, the smoake will issue out threat. Also you may perceiue if a peece be without cracke or flawes, in striking vpon the same with some iron toole; &amp; if the peece be without crack, shee will haue a cleere and sharp sound being vnloaden, otherwise she will haue a harsh or dull sound.</p>
            <p>Any Gunner skilfull and experienced in the Art, may dispart any great peece seuen seuerall wayes, but the readiest and easiest way is to thrust your priming y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron into the touch hole of the peece, downe to the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:178591:11"/> part of the concaue of the peece, and with your knife make a marke on the said priming yron, iust with the height of the vtmost part or highest part of the mettall there. Then draw out the same priming yron, setting the same vpright at the mouth of the peece, so as the lowest end of the said priming yron touch the lowest part of the concaue there also, &amp; hard by the vpper part of the mettall at the mouth of the peece with your knife make another marke on the said priming iron, the distance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene those two markes is the true disparture of that peece.</p>
            <p>To anie one or moe peeces of Ordnance of like length and height, that shooteth one quantitie of one like powder and bullet, may be made a precise table of randons: but a thing vnpossible to make one perfect ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of randons to seurall peeces of contrarie length and height, discharged with one like or vnlike powder and bullet, although diuerse authors haue affirmed the same may be done, and haue giuen out rules thereof: for the variable length of the peeces, the differing weights of the bullets, and the sundry forces of diuers kindes of powder, must and will alter in each of these cases.</p>
            <p>By experimenting diuerse shots out of anie one or moe peeces of Ordnance, of like length and height, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with one quantitie of one like powder and bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, I could artificially describe how to make an instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which set vpon the breech of the peece, the visuall line thereof should shew what length the said peece re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth to reach any marke within the vtmost randon of the said peece, as also should shew the number of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees the said peece is eleuated at, and how farre the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:178591:12"/> said peece would conuey her bullet at any degree of the randon, or what distance any mark is different from the peece, and how much higher or lower the said marke is than the point blanke of the said peece, the said peece loaden at euery time with one like quantitie of one like powder, wad and bullet, and of like temper: but foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the same will not hold in all peeces of contrary length &amp; height, neither in any one peece of Ordnance discharged with her due loading of diuerse kindes of powder, it were a thing not conuenient to shew the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons therof, for that the same requireth a long discourse, and would be to no great purpose, vnlesse the same might be a generall rule for all peeces, of what length and height soeuer.</p>
            <p>You may discharge any peece of Ordnance by the beame of the sunne a pretty distance from the same, the sunne bright shining, and the day cleere and hote, in taking a broad bright bason; setting the same so on the side of the carriage of the peece against the touch-hole, that it may strike the reflex of the sunne beame backe vpon a traine of fine powder layde vpon and about the touch-hole of the peece, in the midst whereof lay a little fine lint dipped in molten brimstone, and on the same a crystall stone: and standing thirty or forty yards from the same (or further, if you thinke good) by the ayde of three or foure glasses well steeled, you may cast the beame of the sunne directly against the centre of the bason, which will so multiply the heate, that it will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently fire the traine, and so discharge the peece. Or you may giue fire to any peece of Ordnance with a burning glasse; but then you must be neere to the peece, which will be perillous, for feare of the reuerse of the wheele,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:178591:12"/> except you make a traine, and so drawing the beame of the sunne into a point like a pin head through the center of the glasse, you shall so multiply the heate, that it will presently giue fire to the peece. I reade that <hi>Archimedes</hi> by his skill in Geometry and in the Art Perspectiue, did from off the wals of Siracusa (the Citie being besieged by the Romanes) fire their Nauie riding in the roade without, onely by the ayde of glasses; as also diuerse of our owne countrey-men by the aide of glasses haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimented many notable and strange conclusions, to their euerlasting fame.</p>
            <p>You may also with a quart or pottle of any liquor, as wine, water, ale, or beere, discharge any peece of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, in putting into the touch-hole of the peece the end of a peece of match of a yard or fiue quarters long, well soaked in moulten brimstone, the peece being well primed: and setting or making fast to the side of the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the peece, any little halfe firkin or woodden vessell that will hold a gallon or pottle of liquor, filling the same halfe full of lymestone new burnt and vnquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, &amp; take the lightest &amp; whitest stones you can finde (for those are best burnt:) then take three or foure of those stones, and beate the same into fine powder, and mixe with three or foure handfuls of the same, as much powder and brimstone beaten verie fine, laying the same amids the vessell vpon the stones, rowling the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end of the match in that receipt, and then fill vp the vessell with other like stones, powring vpon the same as much liquor aforesaid as would fill halfe the tub: the which will melt the stones into dust, and drink vp all the liquor, and with the heat therof will presently fire the brimstone, which kindling the match, will dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:178591:13"/> the peece: and if you make the said liquor see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hote, and poure it into the vessell, it will so worke therein, that if the vessell be not all the better girded, it will burst it in peeces.</p>
            <p>If in seruice, or at any other time, you haue occasion to shoot diuers shots in one or mo peeces, the day being verie windie, so that it bloweth away the priming pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der laid about the touch-hole of the peece, to preuent that inconuenience, if you take a little tough clay, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the same wel in your hand, and laying the same vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the mettall of the peece on the windie side, in maner of ½ a circle, one or two inches from the touch-hole, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout one inch height, it wil hinder the wind from blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the priming powder away, so that you may giue fire at pleasure.</p>
            <p>Any peece of Ordnance being discharged in the night, the report or roare thereof will be heard further than if shee had been discharged in the day, the weather of like calmnesse: &amp; the report wil sound further down the winde than against the same, and further on the sea than on the land, the ayre quiet and the sea calme. Also if you make a hole in the ground fiue or six inches deep, and lay your eare close thereto, you shall heare the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of any peece of Ordnance discharged from farre more perfectly than standing or walking: by experience, it hath beene often tryed, that the sound of the Canons discharged at the siege of diuerse Holds, hath bin heard verie neere fortie miles.</p>
            <p>Some Gunners hold opinion, that the reuerse of anie peece of Ordnance discharged, is not before the fire be cleane expulsed out of the concaue of the peece into the open aire: but therin they erre; for experience sheweth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:178591:13"/> that the peece and carriage beginneth to recoyle in that moment, assoone as euer the powder fired within the peece, beginneth to thrust it selfe out, the violent expulsiue motion whereof striuing forward, causeth the peece to recoyle, but the rore or report of the peece dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, is not before the fire be expulsed out of the peece. Also some hold opinion, that the force of the fire departing from the peece, causeth the mettall to quiuer or shake: and to assure themselues, they haue for tryall clapt to the bottome of a glasse a little quantitie of wax or pitch, and filling the glasse with water, set the same vpon the highest part of the mettall, about the middle of the peece; and because the same hath broken in shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers or fallen, they thinke their opinion is strong. But my opinion is contrary; for if the mettal of the peece at her discharge doe any whit quiuer or shake, the peece would eyther burst in shiuers or rent it selfe: for I hold that it is the very ayre or violent blast proceeding from the fire, eyther out of the mouth of the peece, or touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hole, or both, and withall the sudden reuerse of the peece, that doth cause the thing so set vpon the vpper face of the mettall, to burst or fall off: and for the better triall hereof, I asked the opinion of a souldier, who for a trespasse committed was enioyned to ride the Canon, who confidently affirmed, he could perceiue no quiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the mettall of the peece, but that the ayre which issued out of the mouth and touch-hole of the peece did somewhat astonish and shake him.</p>
            <p>A ball or bullet of wild-fire shot out of a Chamber or Morter peece, hauing one or mo vents made vpon anie one part thereof to kindle the ball, although for a little motion the said vents burneth from you in the range
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:178591:14"/> thereof, by reason they are first fired, and stand neerest to the peece mouth before the deliuerie thereof, yet for the greater part of the range the ball will turne and burne with the said vents towards you; as by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting the same you may see: for reason teacheth, that any solid thing violently driuen, flyeth with that part formost that is most ponderous and weightie, which in this case must needs be that part of the ball vnburnt, or which is not vented.</p>
            <p>A ball of wilde-fire discharged out of any peece of Ordnance, hauing but one vent, the swifter that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit is in burning, the further it wil range, the peece be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing presently discharged as the bal is fired: and the slow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the receit is, the lesse distance will the range be: and any ball hauing but one vent, will range further and burne longer than hauing diuers vents.</p>
            <p>A ball of wild-fire made to burne in the water, being fired and throwne therein, that part will appeare first a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the water that is lightest (to wit) that part wherein the vent is, the which ball will not burne perfectly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the superficies of the water, vntill the ½ thereof be burnt and emptied, and so beeing filled with ayre doth cause the other part to swimme and burne aboue the water.</p>
            <p>A ball of wilde-fire made neuer so artificially shot out of a morter, chamber, or other great peece of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, the peece hauing her full loading in powder, that is vsed to giue her in shooting a bullet of mettall, will cause the said ball to burst in peeces, and therefore the said peece must bee loaden with a proportionall charge in powder to the weight of the ball, which will not be aboue ½ the weight of the ordinarie charge vsed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:178591:14"/> to shoot a bullet of mettall.</p>
            <p>A ball of wild-fire discharged out of any peece of great Ordinance, beeing vented or bored through crosse-wise, and primed full of powder to take fire, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the flame of the fire in the burning of the said ball issue out at euery end of the said vents, that, is foure seuerall waies, yet in the motion or range thereof, the greatest part of the flame and fire will issue out but at one or at two vents at the most, which will bee those vents in that part of the ball that is towards the peece; for the violent mouing of the bal through the aire, doth cause the flame to shew it selfe, and to burne most on the contrary part against which it flieth: the which flame will shew it selfe as it were a taile, or traine following the ball in his motion. And it is to be considered, that in shooting any peece of Ordinance with a fire ball, the peece would be loaden with lesse than halfe her ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry charge in powder, or with the one halfe at the most, that is, with one ladle full of powder, the which put gently home with the tampion on the end of your ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer staffe, put in the ball close to the powder, priming the same well before you put it in, and after the ball put in a handfull of powder close to the ball, so shall you be sure the same will take fire, and not burst in the flight or range being well wolled and marted.</p>
            <p>The receits wherewith bals of wild-fire or other fire-workes are made being slow, may be made more strong and to burne more furiously, by adding a little bruized powder to the receits, working the same well together: and any fire-work whose receits bee too forcible in bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, may be made more slow, by adding a quantity of some liquide receit thereunto.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:178591:15"/>
            <p>A ball or bullet of wilde-fire discharged out of any peece of Ordnance in a cleere day, at any marke within the reach of the peece, cannot be discerned in his range, nor seen to burn before it light on the ground. And any ball of fire-worke discharged out of any peece of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance at any mark in the darke night, may be perceiued by the eye all the range thereof: and the more darker the night is that the same is so discharged, the better you may discerne the same: but in the beginning of the range, the eye is not able to discerne it so perfectly as in the latter part thereof; neyther doth the ball burne so forcibly, nor giue such light in his swift motion (that is, in the first part of the range) as in the latter part of his motion, when it declineth towards the ground.</p>
            <p>If you take Arsnicke and Sulphur, of each like quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie, and beat the same very fine, and then boyle the same in a couered pot, and then kindle the same with a candle, letting no other light be seen; the standers about the same will seeme monstrous strange one to another.</p>
            <p>Or if you take <hi>Aqua composita</hi> and Salt, and pound the same together, and fire the same in the darke where no other light may be seene, the beholders will seeme as they were dead.</p>
            <p>I read in <hi>Albertus Magnus,</hi> and diuers other such Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, how to make strange lights: such as would pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise the same, may haue recourse to their works.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:178591:15"/>
               <head>Deuises of certaine seruiceable Fire-workes, verie necessarie to be vsed both for Sea and Land seruices.</head>
               <p>TO arme Pikes to defend a Ship or a breach, or to enter the same, take strong canuas, the which cut, sewed &amp; tyed hard on the pike with marlin cord, as the draught marked with the letter A. sheweth; fill the same with this receit compounded and wrought together (to wit) Powder bruised, eight parts; Peter in Roch, one part; Peter in Meale, one part; Sulphur in Meale, two parts; Rozin roch, three parts; Turpentine, one part; Linseed oyle, one part; Verdegrease, ½ part; Bole armoniacke, ⅓ part; Bay salt ⅓ part; Colophonia, ⅙ part: and if you thinke good, you may put thereto of Arsnick ⅛ part: then coate the same ouer with this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid mixture molten in a pan or coating pot (to wit) Pitch, foure parts; Linseed oyle, one part; Turpentine, ⅕ part; Sulphur, one part; Tarre, ⅓ part; Tallow, one part. And assoone as this is cold, bore two holes in each of the same an inch deepe, with a sharpe yron or bodkin, filling the same with fine bruised powder, putting in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie hole a little sticke of two or three inches length, which are to be taken out when you would fire the same. This composition will burn furiously. If you please you may make fast to the same receit on your Pike certaine light pipes or canes of yron or brasse of sixe or seuen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches length, being Pistol or Caliuer bore, as the draught B. sheweth, placing the touch-hole thereof close to the canuas, boring the said canuas thorow, and priming the same with fine powder, &amp; vpon the same paste a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle paper, &amp; then coat the same ouer as aboue is said, the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:178591:16"/> which charged with powder and bullet will doe great execution in a throng, either to offend or defend.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure A: pike fitted for fireworks</figDesc>
                  <p>A</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure B: pike fitted for fireworks</figDesc>
                  <p>B</p>
               </figure>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:178591:16"/>
               <p>You may arme a Dart, a Iauelin, Partizan, or such like weapon, to do excellent good seruice, being in the hand of a valiant souldier, as you see the figure C. the which may be filled with the selfe like receit as is taught to arme pikes with wild-fire, which would be a very good weapon to throw into the sides or sailes of ships; or you may place vpon the staffe of your Iauelin cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Pistoll barrels of one length, about ten or twelue inches, letting the same into the wood round about the staffe a little, as you put a Pistoll barrell into the stocke, as the draught D. sheweth, which staffe must haue sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance at the one end, whereto you may naile the same barrels fast at the breech: and about the midst of the same put ouer a hoope of yron as close as euer you can, the which is to be charged in this order following, viz. first charge euery barrel with two inches of powder, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter put in a bullet a little lower than the bore of the same peece; then take of this slow receit following (to wit) bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed powder foure parts, saltpeter in meale one part, lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seed oile 1. part, brimstone finely beaten 1. part, varnish 1 part, and of willow or hazel cole moistened with a little venegar 1. part: all these would be wel wrought together with the hand in some wooden vessell, til you feele that it will cling together, of which you must put in after the bullet two inches, and thrust the same together with a rammer stick: then againe put in other two inches of powder, and after a bullet, and lastly two inches of this slow receit, vntill you haue filled euery of the said bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels within ½ inch of the mouth, the which is to be filled vp with the said slow receit &amp; powder bruised &amp; mixed together, that it may the sooner fire: this done, binde a paper ouer the mouthes of the same, vntill you would
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:178591:17"/> occupie them, and giuing fire to any one of the same, it will fire all the other, and euery one will discharge three or foure shots a peece, one after another, to the hurt of
<figure>
                     <figDesc>Figure C: weapon fitted for fireworks</figDesc>
                     <p>C</p>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Figure D: weapon fitted for fireworks</figDesc>
                     <p>D</p>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:178591:17"/> the enemie being vsed in seruice either to offend or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, and to the pleasure of the beholders, being vsed in triumph with bullets of receit rolled in fine tow, and coated with brimstone.</p>
               <p>If you would defend some narrow roome, or would enter vp a paire of stairs, where you cannot weild a long weapon, you may make a logget, whose staffe shal bee but three or foure foote long: arming the same with the like receit as I haue shewed to arme pikes, whereon you may place certaine pipes of brasse or iron charged as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is taught: &amp; if you wil you may put into the end of the staffe a Rapier blade with a skrew to take off and on at your pleasure, as the draught E. hereunder sheweth.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure E: logget fitted for fireworks, with rapier blade on the end</figDesc>
                  <p>E</p>
               </figure>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:178591:18"/>
               <p>Also you may arme a Partezan, Iauelin, or Fork with fire-worke, to offend or defend a breach, ship, or any place of defence, and to shoot euery of them seuen or eight Pistol or Caliuer bullets; in nailing a plate of iron crosse the pike or point of the said Iauelin, or betweene the graines of the Fork, piercing certain holes through the same, vnto which with a strong wyer you may make fast on either side so many pipes of iron of 7. or 8. inches length as you think conuenient to fix vpon either or any of the said weapons; &amp; charging the same with powder, bullet, and wad, you may cause the same to fire one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another, in filling a role of canuas sewed together as the draught F. sheweth, with slow receit and coated as afore is taught, the which placed arteficially vpon the said short barrels or pipes, as the draught G. H. shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and primed with sine powder directly against the touch holes of the said short barrels, pasting a little pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ouer the same, siring the said traines at both the
<figure>
                     <figDesc>Figure F: weapon fitted for fireworks</figDesc>
                     <p>F</p>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Figure G: weapon fitted for fireworks</figDesc>
                     <p>G</p>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Figure H: weapon fitted for fireworks</figDesc>
                     <p>H</p>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:178591:18"/> ends, which as they burne shall still discharge the short peeces one after another, to the great good of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant.</p>
               <p>To offend or defend any narrow passage, or for diuers other militarie seruices, you may place vpon the point or pike of any Halbard a deuise of fire-worke, in maner as is taught to arme pikes, made of the same like receit, &amp; coated with the self like coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: and if you please you may make fast therto half a dozen or mo short pipes, like Pistoll bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, of 7. or 8 inches length, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with powder and bullet as this draught sheweth.</p>
               <p>Or you may make a seruice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able halbard by which you may know the houre of the night, by viewing the North starre, and guards (commonly called the lesser Beare) which compasseth about the north star once euery 24. hours, very necessary for all Leaders or Cōmanders of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary men, by placing vpon the bill or axe of the Halbard a roundel diuided into 24. equall diuisions, and traced and drawn withan index or pointer hauing a hole pierced through the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The order how to make the instrument, as also how to find out any houre in any night that
<figure>
                     <figDesc>weapon fitted for fireworks</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:178591:19"/> the said starres may bee seene, you may learne in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenteenth Chapter of the Art of Nauigation, written by <hi>Martin Curtis,</hi> who sheweth the same in such a plaine and easie manner, that any vnlearned man hauing a sharpe wit may vnderstand the same.</p>
               <p>To burne the sailes of ships a prettie distance off, or to fire thatched houses, corne-stacks, or any combusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble matter apt to burn, when as you cannot come to the same, it is good to make certaine strong bowes, to bend either with a rack or gassel, or otherwise, and to shoot out of the same strong arrowes armed with wild-fire, &amp; headed as the draught I, sheweth: the composition is to be made as is taught to arme Pikes with fire-work, which arrowes may do great good for diuers seruices.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure I: bow and arrow fitted for fireworks</figDesc>
                  <p>I</p>
               </figure>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:178591:19"/>
               <p>To burne bridges, woodden gates, &amp;c. or to doe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other militarie seruices, if you can come to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the same with some such liquid composition as I haue shewed for the coating of fire-workes, melting in the same a good quantitie of bruised brimstone, and stic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the same arrowes of wild-fire made in propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as the draught K, sheweth, the which may be made of the selfe like receits, as is taught to arme pikes with fire-workes, which will vndoubtedly set the same a fire, for the receit is so forcible that it will burne in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>To charge trunkes to shoot little bals of wild-fire, either to offend or defend, you must charge the same with two inches of good powder, and then with a bal of wild-fire a little lower than the concaue of the trunke, bored through crossewise, and primed full of fine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<figure>
                     <figDesc>Figure K: arrows fitted for fireworks</figDesc>
                     <p>K</p>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:178591:20"/> and lastly with two inches of slow receit, and then againe with powder, and then a ball of slow receit, vntill you haue filled the same within ¼ of an inch of the mouth, which would be filled vp with fine powder and receit mixed together. The order how to charge a trunk appeareth by the draught L. the draught M. sheweth the proportion of a trunke already charged and fired, and the draught N. sheweth how certaine pipes of brasse or yron may bee placed on a trunke, which beeing loaden each of them with a Pistoll or Caliuer charge of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and bullet, will do great execution.</p>
               <p>The bullet or ball of wild-fire, or button, as some Gunners terme it, would be made in this manner. Take vntwisted match, tow, or hempe, the which would bee moistened in <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> or sod in saltpeter water, then take of bruised powder sixe parts, of saltpeter one part, of brimstone finely beaten one part, of cole made of light wood, moistened with a little linseed oyle and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine wrought together one part; then laying the tow or ocam abrode in thicknesse of the backe of a knife, and as brode as a great oyster shell, put into the same as much of the receit as you can grasp together in your fist, and tying the same hard with packthreed, coate the same ouer with molten brimstone, and when you would vse the same, bore it through crossewise with a bodkin, and fill the holes full of fine powder bruised. Or you may make bullets of wild-fire to shoot out of a trunke or out of a peece of great Ordnance the which will bee as hard as a stone, and needeth no coating, the which being a little burnt will cleaue to any thing at which you shoote the same, in taking of sulphur in meale sixe parts, of rozin in meale three parts, melting the same
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:178591:20"/> in some pot or pan ouer a slow fire, then take of stone pitch one part, of hard waxe one part, of tarre ¼ part, of <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> ½ part, of linseed oyle ½ part, of verdegreese ¼ part, of camphire ⅛ part, melting all these together like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, and stirre into the same of Peter in meale two parts; and taking the same from the fire, put therin foure parts of bruised powder, working the same well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in your hands, and rol the same round, of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse you meane to make the balles of, boring two ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les through the same acrosse, which when you would occupie, would be primed full of bruised powder: these bals being cold will grow very hard, and fired will burne furiously, not diminishing in quantitie beeing burnt to ashes, the ashes whereof will kindle an oaken boord.</p>
               <p>To cut the cables, shrouds or mastes of shippes, a good pretie distance off, beeing in sea seruice, there is deuised out of great Ordinance to shoot certaine bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets that shall open and shut with a ioynt in the head, as
<figure>
                     <figDesc>Figure L: weapon fitted for fireworks</figDesc>
                     <p>L</p>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Figure M: weapon fitted for fireworks</figDesc>
                     <p>M</p>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Figure N: weapon fitted for fireworks</figDesc>
                     <p>N</p>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:178591:21"/> you see a paire of compasses, the armes or legs whereof are made in proportion to the blade of a knife, taper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, and bowing sharpe towards the point as the draught hereunder sheweth, where the draught O. sheweth how the same is to bee put into the peece after the powder and wad, and the draught P, sheweth how the same in his violent motion flieth through the ayre like a sythe, beeing shot out of any peece of great Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure O: jointed bullet to be loaded</figDesc>
                  <p>O</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure P: jointed bullet after being fired</figDesc>
                  <p>P</p>
               </figure>
               <p>There is also deuised for like seruice aforesaid, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinde of bullet, treble ioynted at the head, with streight armes sharpe at the point, to shoot out of great Ordinance: the draught marked with the letter Q. sheweth how the same is to bee put into the peece; and the draught R, sheweth how the same slieth through the ayre like a galtrop, beeing violently driuen by the force of the powder out of the peece: the chaine or linkes are to keepe the same streight in his motion or range.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:178591:21"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure Q: triple-jointed bullet to be loaded</figDesc>
                  <p>Q</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure R: triple-jointed bullet after being fired</figDesc>
                  <p>R</p>
               </figure>
               <p>To cut the tackle and shrouds of ships, it is good to cast halfe bullets of iron or lead; vnto euery of which make fast a barre of yron, wrought either three square or foure square, of the greatnesse of a mans finger, about fourteene or sixteene inches length, with a loope at the end, vnto which a ring of iron is to be put, that the same may close and shut as the draught S. sheweth, shewing also how you must put the same into the peece: and the draught T. sheweth how the same flieth in his mouing through the ayre. Or to the said halfe bullets you may make bars in proportion of a knife blade, with a round
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:178591:22"/> ioynt at the end to open and shut, the which kinde of bullets may as well bee made to shoote out of Muskets as out of great Ordinance, to the great annoy of the enemie, especially in sea-seruice, as the figure V. W. sheweth.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure S: weapon for cutting tackle and shrouds of ships, to be loaded</figDesc>
                  <p>S</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure T: weapon for cutting tackle and shrouds of ships, after being fired</figDesc>
                  <p>T</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure V: weapon for cutting tackle and shrouds of ships, to be shot out of a musket</figDesc>
                  <p>V</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure W: weapon for cutting tackle and shrouds of ships, to be shot out of a musket</figDesc>
                  <p>W</p>
               </figure>
               <p>Also to cut the tackle of shippes, or to doe many other good seruices, either with Musket or other peece of great Ordinance, it is good to chaine together two bullets in manner as the draught hereunder sheweth, where the letter X. sheweth how the same is to bee put into the peece, and the letter Y. sheweth how the same flyeth through the ayre, being discharged out of any peece of great Ordinance, or out of any Musket.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:178591:22"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure X: two bullets chained together for cutting the tackle of ships, to be loaded into a musket or larger weapon</figDesc>
                  <p>X</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure Y: two bullets chained together for cutting the tackle of ships, after being fired from a musket or larger weapon</figDesc>
                  <p>Y</p>
               </figure>
               <p>Also for like purpose aforesaid, if you take a small y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron chain with handsome linkes, rolling the same round together, so as the same may goe easily into the peece close down to the wad, the same being again discharged out of the peece, will spread it selfe as the draught mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with the letter Z. sheweth.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure Z: small iron chain rolled up for loading into a firearm; the same chain unrolled after being fired</figDesc>
                  <p>Z</p>
               </figure>
               <p>There is also vsed to cut the mastes or shrouds of ships, or to boudge the same, &amp;c. to charge great Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance with bullets of yron, hauing a great square barre through the same of two foote length or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:178591:23"/> sharp at the one end &amp; round at the other, about ½ the diameter of the cilinder of the peece, &amp; on the mids thereof a bullet about ½ part of an inch lower than the height of the hollow cilinder of the peece, as the draught marked with A, sheweth, these are called crosse-barres: when the same is to be put into the peece, the peece be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loaden with her due of powder and wad, some vse to put vpon the small end thereof a good quantitie of old Ocam, wrapping the same fast about with marlin cord, and some vse to put atampion of wood vpon the end thereof, and some wrap a peece of an old saile or other old cloth fast vpon the end of the bar, and so dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the same.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure A: two-foot iron bar, sharp at one end and round at the other, with a bullet in the middle, for cutting the masts or shrouds of ships</figDesc>
                  <p>A</p>
               </figure>
               <p>Being in sea seruice, if the enemie will needes boord you, and that you intend not to yeeld, it is necessarie to haue in store and readinesse diuers hollow bullets, made of two plates of iron or other mettall, so as the one may close round vpon the other like a boxe, the which filled with pebble stones, square peeces of yron called dice shot, Musket bullets, and such like, and discharged out of a murdering peece will do wonderfull hurt: behold the draught ensuing. Or, if you fill cases of wood made like vnto a lanthorne full of pebble stones, dice shor, musket bullets, peeces of yron, or such like, dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the same out of any peece of great Ordinance
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:178591:23"/> (especially out of a murdering peece) wil do great execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion against such as are to enter a breach, a bridge, a gate, a ship, &amp;c.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>hollow bullet filled with pebbles, iron dice shot, musket bullets, etc., shown after being fired and its contents scattering; wooden case shaped like a lantern filled with similar pieces, before firing</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>If you bee to enter a ship or other place where you feare there is some traine laid to blow you vp, you may preuent the same by making certaine purses of canuas filled halfe full of good corne powder, and with eight or tenne firie bullets of an inch or an inch ½ height, such as I haue taught to put in trunkes, and filling the other part of the purse with such slow receit as there is also taught, you may when you thinke good (the receit bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well fired) throw the same from you, which will burst in peeces after the lighting on the ground, and disperse the said inclosed bullets here and there, which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:178591:24"/> bullets will burne furiously, and if there bee any traine of powder laid neare, will presently fire the same. The said purses are very good to throw out of hand, or may bee shot out of a morter peece amongst men in battell ray to disorder them, or into a towne; the draught B. sheweth how to fill the purse as here is taught, and the letter C. sheweth the proportion of it, beeing made vp, filled and coated ouer.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure B: canvas purse filled with bullets</figDesc>
                  <p>B</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure C: canvas purse filled with bullets, filled up with a flammable "slow receit" described earlier</figDesc>
                  <p>C</p>
               </figure>
               <p>To shoot a ball of wild-fire out of a Canon, Culue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, or other great peece of Ordinance in time of ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, amongst the enemies a farre off, or into townes, or in triumphs before Princes or great personages, take strong canuas doubled, and cut out a peece as round as the circumference of a circle, iust the height of the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter of the concaue of the Peece out of which it is to be shot, the which sewed sure round about all sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing one inch, fill the same full of this receit following (to wit) powder bruised eight parts, Peter meale two parts, Peter roch one part, rozin roch like pepper cornes two parts, Turpentine ½ part, Linseede oyle one part, Sulphur meale one part, Sulphur roch one part, bole armoniacke ⅓ part, Verdegreese ¼ part, Colophonia ⅙ part. All these things mixed in a tray or some such like woodden vessell, and wraught well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:178591:24"/> with the hand, fill the said ball therewith as hard as you can; then sewing vp the hole and woolling and marling the same well, coate the same ouer with molten brimstone; and with a sharpe yron a little greater than a bodkin, bore two or three holes crosse through the same ball, priming the same full of fine bruised pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and when you would shoot the same, loade the peece but with ½ quantitie of her common charge in powder, and after put in the ball close to the said powder, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter put in a good handfull of powder close to the ball with the tampion on the end of your rammer staffe, the peece mounted about twelue or fourteene degrees will cause the ball to range aboue foure and twentie score paces. If you would haue the ball to make a pleasant range, mount the peece aboue thirtie degrees; and if the transome of the cariage will not suffer it, then you may dip the lower end of the cariage into a hole made in the earth for the purpose, the draught D, sheweth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of such a bullet.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure D: canvas bullet filled with the flammable recipe described immediately above, to be shot as a ball of wildfire out of a cannon or other heavy artillery</figDesc>
                  <p>D</p>
               </figure>
               <p>To shoote a ball of wilde-fire out of a Chamber or Morter peece, you must charge the peece with powder according to the proportion of her chamber, and quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of the ball or bullet that she is to shoot, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:178591:25"/> to the distance the ball is to range, and then take a close wad as hard as you can put home to the powder, and after put in the said ball, first making three or foure vents therein within the compasse of a shilling, an inch or two inches deepe with a bodkin, priming the same with fine bruised powder, and be sure when you put the same into the peece, that the vents be vppermost next to the mouth of the peece, iust in the center or midst of the concaue thereof, then take a peece of gunmatch, or a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle hay twisted with your hand, and after the ball is in the peece as is said, put the same round about the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the bullet, &amp; with a small woodden wedge beat the same close round about the bal, between the said bal and the mettal of the peece, so as no powder fal into the peece, wherby the same might be discharged before the said bal were wel kindled with the traine which you are to make at the mouth of the peece. This done, prime the peece well at the touch-hole, laying a little powder on some brode stone as a train to fire the same readily, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the same with some cloth til the bal be wel fired, lest some spark issuing from the bal, fire the peece too soon. And when you see the ball is wel kindled, take away the cloth, and giue fire to the train at the touch-hole, and so shooting the same amongst men in battell ray, or into a town amongst thatched houses, or corn-stacks, this kind of fire-work wil do excellent good seruice: the letter E, sheweth the proportion of such a bullet to be shot out of a Chamber or Morter peece: but if you be to shoot out of your Morter or Chamber peece bullets of stone or of mettall into some Hold or Town, then you need doe no more but onely loading the peece with her dutie of powder, wad and bullet, giuing fire to the traine at the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:178591:25"/> touch-hole, and giuing the peece her due length, she will performe your wished desire.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure E: bullet to be shot as a ball of wildfire out of a chamber or mortar piece</figDesc>
                  <p>E</p>
               </figure>
               <p>To make balls of wild-fire to shoot out of a Chamber or morter peece, that being recharged shal stick in wod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den gates, ship sides, or such like, make of those balls I haue taught to shoot out of a Canon or Culuering, the which filled as ful &amp; as hard as you can, with the like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit as there is taught, and woolled well &amp; coated ouer, make certaine peeces of yron sharpe at the point of two inches length, with a skrew of ¾ of an inch long at the one end to scrue into the bal, &amp; hard by the same a ioint with a shoulder, that you may at pleasure, put the other end together close to the vtter side of the bal; the which nails or sharpe pieces of iron skrewed in to the shoulder into the ball (the ball being made somthing lower than the concaue of the peece) being discharged out of the peece, will stick in any soft obiect, as wood or such like: for the forcible motion of the bullet or ball, will thrust the said pieces of yron stiffe out in their ioints, so that lighting vpon any resisting obiect (except stone) wil stick in the same: the draught following noted with F, shewes how the same is to be put into the peece, &amp; the letter G, how the ioints do stretch themselues in the violent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therof, discharged out of a Chāber or morter peece.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:178591:26"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure F: ball of wildfire with sharp pieces of iron attached, to be shot out of a chamber or mortar piece and stick in wooden gates, ship's sides, or other such objects (shown before loading)</figDesc>
                  <p>F</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure G: ball of wildfire from figure F shown in flight</figDesc>
                  <p>G</p>
               </figure>
               <p>Or you may make bals to throw out of hand into the sides or sayles of ships of the receit aforesaid, in skrew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the ball round about the vtter side thereof, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine pieces of yron, made sharpe at the ends, like an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders tongue, as the draught H hereunder sheweth.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure H: ball of wildfire like that in figures F and G, to be thrown out of hand into the sides or sails of ships</figDesc>
                  <p>H</p>
               </figure>
               <p>You may also make another kinde of fire-ball that shall burne furiously, and giue a great light, that shall sticke in any resisting obiect that you are to throwe the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:178591:26"/> same into, in taking three or foure peeces of yron of like length, made sharpe at the point, letting the one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the other in the mids, so as the one may crosse the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther iustly, and taking of goose grease or swines grease one part, of tarre ½ part, of pitch two parts, of <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> ½ part, of linseed oyle one part, of turpentine one part, of verdegrease ¼ part, of waxe ½ part, of gumme ¼ part, of Saltpeter meale one part, of Sulphur meale one part: melt all these together ouer a slowe fire, and in that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid mixture dip a good quantitie of Tow and linnen rags, and after rub the same well in bruised powder, the which rolled hard round about the peeces of yron a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, binde the same about with small wyer or pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threed, and when you would occupy the same, bore two holes crosse thorow the same, filling the same with bruised powder: the draught I, sheweth the proportion of such a ball as here is spoken of. This kind of fire-ball may be made to shoote out of great Ordnance, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the same round, as aboue is said, without the peeces of yron: or you may make of these balls to throw with
<figure>
                     <figDesc>Figure I: ball of wildfire to burn furiously with great light and stick in any resisting object, with three or four iron points attached</figDesc>
                     <p>I</p>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Figure K: ball of wildfire like that in figure I without the iron pieces, for shooting out of heavy artillery</figDesc>
                     <p>K</p>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:178591:27"/> with hand amongst men in battell aray, or into ships, or you may vse the same in a triumph for pleasure in tying a cord of ¾ long thereunto, as the letter K, sheweth.</p>
               <p>To make a fire-ball to burne in the water, take pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der bruised ten parts, Peter in meale two parts, Peter roch one part, Sulphur meale three parts, Rozin roch three parts, Turpentine one part, Linseed oyle one part, Camphire ¼ part, Arsnick ¼ part, Verdegreese ¼ part, bole armoniacke ¼ part, cornes of bay salt ¼ part, filings of y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron ⅕ part, quicke-siluer ⅛ part. All these things being well wrought together with the hand in some wooden vessell, double a peece of canuasse, &amp; cut out of the same a round peece of three inches, or three inches ½ diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which being well sewed fill the same with this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, and binding the same strongly about with packe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threed, and coating the same ouer with molten pitch, or with the mixture taught to coate pykes of wilde-fire, make therein but one vent of an inch deepe, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming therein fine bruised powder, and put into the hole a little sticke of two inches length, which when you would occupie you may take out, and letting the same
<figure>
                     <figDesc>hogshead full of water carrying a fireball</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:178591:27"/> burne a while in your hand, cast the bal into some hogs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head full of water, or into a riuer or pond, and the same will come vp to the superficies of the water, and burne furiously: the draught last before sheweth the manner thereof.</p>
               <p>Or you may make a ball of wild-fire to burne in the water in this maner: take brimstone in meale two parts, and melt the same ouer a slow fire, and therin put of salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter in meale one part, of gum ⅓ part, of wax ¼ part, and taking this compound from the fire, stir into the same of bruised powder three parts, working the same well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, moistening the same with a little oyle of linseed or <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> and putting this receit into a peece of can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uasse sewed vp round and marled and coated ouer as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is taught, boring a hole therein of an inch deep, and priming the same full of bruised powder: this ball will burn in the water whensoeuer you would vse the same, but is not of such force as the ball filled with other mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. You may make balls of this receit to shoot out of a Morter peece, boring thorow the same two holes, the one crossing the other, or boring three holes in the same, into the center or mids of the ball, as the draught L sheweth.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Figure L: ball of wildfire that will burn (less forcefully than the previous one) in the water, to be shot out of a mortar piece</figDesc>
                  <p>L</p>
               </figure>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:178591:28"/>
               <p>It is good eyther for seruice on sea to burne the sailes of shipps, or on the land for disordering men in battell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray being neere, or for diuers other militarie seruices, to haue certaine short muskets of an inch or very neere an inch bore, out of which you may shoot eyther chained bullets, or halfe a score pistoll bullets, or halfe a dozen harquebuz bullets at one shot; or you may shoot out of the same fire-arrowes made with strong shafts fethered with horne, or with common feathers, glewed &amp; bound on with threed: when you are to shoot a fire-arrow out of any of these peeces, you must not giue the peece her full loading of powder, but rather ⅔ parts thereof, and then put in a close wad after the powder, and put in the arrow close to the said wadde, firing the same at the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end without the mouth of the peece, as you see the
<figure>
                     <figDesc>soldier aiming a musket with fire-arrows</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:178591:28"/> draught: which being well fired, you may discharge the same at your pleasure. The string made fast to the end of the fire-worke, is to keepe the arrow streight in his passage, being shot eyther with or against the winde.</p>
               <p>For the like seruice aforenamed, it is good to haue certaine strong bowes to shoot fierie shafts, something stronger and longer than ordinarie shafts: for making the fire-worke fast to them, the which being fired and discharged out of the bow by a skilfull Archer, hauing a strong arme, will doe excellent good seruice for diuers occasions, as by the draught hereunder you may see.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>soldier aiming a bow with a fire-arrow</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:178591:29"/>
               <p>I might here adioyne varietie of seruiceable fire-works, as also shew many deuices of pleasant fire-works to be vsed in triumphs before great personages; but to the wise these may suffice, who by experimenting these may easily performe the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Here followeth the making and vse of the Geometricall Instrument, called the GVNNERS Quadrant.</head>
               <p>THe Quadrant geometricall is the most common and especiall Instrument vsed amongst the Professors of the art of Gunnerie, most easie to vnderstand of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, both for bringing their peece leuell with anie marke they are to shoot at, as also to shoot at any degree of the randon: the effects whereof I haue not seene set out in any booke of Gunnery, &amp; therefore haue thought good to shew some notable practises by the said Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to bee performed, the making and vse whereof briefly followeth.</p>
               <p>To make a Geometricall Quadrant eyther of met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall or of fine smooth wood, draw foure equall sleight lines, that may cut each other square-wise, of seuen or eight inches length or more; for the larger the lesser error, as you may see in the figure AB, BC, CD, DA, following. And from the center A, draw a slope line to C, called the hipothemisall line, and of some a diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trall line, vpon which if the plum line fall vpon the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter A, looking through the sights E, F, beholding the extreame or highest part of any altitude, the distance, from the middle part of your foote to the base thereof, adding thereto the iust height from your eye, is
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:178591:29"/> the iust height of the said altitude: but if the plum-line fall on the line AB. then any marke that you view through the visuall sights EF, is of equall height or le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell with your eye. Or putting the rule into the concaue of the peece, so that the threed fall on the line AB, then that peece lieth point blanke, or in a streight line with any marke you are to shoot at: or if the plum-line fal on the line AD, the thing you behold is direct vpright; then opening your compasse the iust length of any one of these squire lines, setting one foote in the center A, with the other foote draw an arke or circumference from the angle D to B, which arke shall be the iust ¼ part of the circumference of a circle, and is called a Quadrant, the which is to bee diuided into ninetie equall diuisions, which is called degrees: which may easily be done, by diuiding the arke into three equall portions, and euery of them into three, so haue you nine equall parts, so that diuiding each of them into two parts makes 18. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall parts, and euery of those into fiue equall parts, will make iust ninetie equall diuisions or degrees: so is your Quadrant finished.</p>
               <p>The scale which is the squire lines BC, and CD, may be diuided into 12. 60. yea 100. or 1000. diuisions, the more the better, for the vse of shadowes, lengths, heights, &amp;c. Where you must remember, that the side CD, is called the right shadow, and sheweth how to measure all heights within the length thereof, but the side BC, is of contrary shadow, which serueth to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure all heights without the length thereof, the vse whereof followeth.</p>
               <p>The rule to which the Quadrant is artificially ioyned would bee two foote in length, diuided in equall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:178591:30"/> and parts with a hollow slit in the midst, vpon which would bee placed a fine plate with a little round hole in the middle thereof, to view any marke setting the rule vpright at the breech of the peece: the said plate would bee made to moue vp or downe at pleasure, by which you may know what length or what inches and parts any peece requireth to reach any marke. The visuall sights placed on the edge of the rule would not bee aboue two or three inches from the ends thereof, and the rule would bee of weight to counterpoize the quadrant, so that when the rule is put vnto the concaue of the peece, the Quadrants weight doe not raise the same.</p>
               <p>Before you beginne to measure the length or height of any altitude, or to know whether any mark you are to shoot at be higher or lower than your platforme, or the cilinder of your peece, it behooueth you first to see whether the base or lowest part of the said mark or alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude bee aboue or vnder point blanke; the which you may know by viewing the same through the sights on the rule, letting the threed fall at libertie on the degrees of the Quadrant. And if the plum-line fall on the line of leuell, then the marke is of equal height with your eye; if the threed fall towards you, the marke is aboue point blanke; if from the line of leuel, it is vnder point blanke. And for the more true and perfect working of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusions following, it is good to make a little hollow skrew in the middle of the hipothemisall line, and to haue a staffe or gunners Iauelin to erect perpendicularly with a little skrew plate of yron on the end at the side thereof, into which turning a skrewed naile through the hole so made in the Quadrant, you may make the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:178591:30"/> same vnmoueable, so as you may lift the same vp or down to behold any marke at pleasure: for no man can hold his hand so precisely but it will shake and moue, and so cause the threed to erre a little.</p>
               <div type="method">
                  <head>How you may by your Geometricall Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant measure the height of any wall, Tower, Steple, Tree, or any altitude approachable.</head>
                  <p>GO towards the same vntil by supposition you think you are near about the length of the height of the same, and then setting the Quadrant to your eye, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king through the visuall sights, beholding the extreame or highest part of the altitude, goe to or from the same vntill the threed and plummet cut or fall vpon the part twelue of right shadow; then measuring how farre it is from the middle part of your foot to the base of the said altitude, thereunto adding the height from your eye to the ground, you haue the iust height of that altitude.</p>
                  <p>The same conclusion is to bee wrought by the sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow or beam of the Sun, in turning the left side of your Quadrant to the Sunne, so as his beames may pierce through the visuall sights of the plummet falling on the part twelue, the distance from the furthest point of that shadow to the base of the altitude is the iust height of the same, being an vpright altitude.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="method">
                  <head>How you may diuers waies finde out any vpright height within the length thereof both by the shadow and without shadow.</head>
                  <p>IF the ground be plaine and that you may goe so neare
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:178591:31"/> to the base of the altitude, that the plum-line may fall on the part one of right shadow; then measuring the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance from the midst of your foote to the base thereof, multiplying that measure by twelue, and adding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the height from your eye to the ground, you haue the true height of that altitude: or letting the Sunne beame pierce through the visuall sights of the plum-line, falling at libertie on the part one of right shadow, measuring and multiplying that measure by twelue, and diuiding by the parts whereon the plum-line hangs, the quotient wil tel you the true height of the same altitude: for this is a generall rule, that looke what part of right shadow is cut by the threed or plum-line, the altitude or vpright height to bee measured is more than that sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, by such proportion as twelue exceedeth the part or diuision of the skale where the threed or plum-line was found.</p>
                  <p>If the threed bee found to fall on the part 2. of right shadow, measure the distance from the midst of your foote to the base of the altitude, sixe times that measure is the height of the same, adding the height from the eye to the ground, for the part 2. is contained in 12. (the diuisions of the scale) six times; or what part soeuer it fal on of right shadow, look how oft that part is contained in 12. so many times as that measure is from the midst of your foote to the base, euer adding the height from your eye, is the true height of the thing you measure. Or in briefe, if the plum-line fall on the part 3. working as is said, foure times that measure is the height of the alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</p>
                  <p>Or if it fall on the part 4. then three times; if on the part 5. two times ⅖ parts of the shadow is the height: if
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:178591:31"/> on the part 6, 2 times: if on the part 7, once &amp; 1/7: if on the part 8, once and ½: if on the part 9, once ⅓: if on the part 10, once and ⅕: if on the part 11, once 1/11 part of the shadow. All these mensurations be to be wrought with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the length of the altitude.</p>
                  <p>In measuring by the points of contrary shadow, which sheweth to measure all altitudes without the length therof, you must multiply the length of the shadow by the point or diuision of the scale wheron the threed fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, diuiding the result by 12, the quotient will shew you the true height of the altitude.</p>
                  <p>Or without shadow, goe so neare to the same that you imagine you are neare within the length thereof, lifting vp the Quadrant orderly, going to or from the same, till through the sights you espie the top or highest part of the altitude, the threed falling on the part 12, standing vpright with your body, and at the midst of your foote make a marke, then goe directly backeward from the same, till through the visuall sights you espie the highest part againe, the threed falling on the part 6 of contrary shadow; and at the midst of your foot make another marke, the distance between those two markes adioyning thereto the height from your eye to the ground, is the true height of the altitude: and your fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thest station is twice the length of the height of the alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, wanting the height from your eye to the ground, which you must euer adde to the worke.</p>
                  <div type="method">
                     <head>Another way.</head>
                     <p>If at the first station the threed fall on the part 6 of contrarie shadow, &amp; at the second station on the part 4, the distance betweene those two markes is the height,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:178591:32"/> adding as before, and the furthest station is three times the length of the altitude you measure from the base therof, the ground being plaine.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="method">
                     <head>Another way.</head>
                     <p>If at the first station the threed fall on the part 4, of contrary shadow, and at the second on the part 3, then the distance betweene your two standings is the height desired, adding as afore, and the furthest station is distant from the base of the altitude foure times the length or height thereof.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="method">
                     <head>Another way.</head>
                     <p>If at the first station the threed fall on the part 3, and at the next the part 2, then the distance betweene those two standings is twice as much as the length of the alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, excepting the height from your eie to the ground, and your furthest station shall be from the base of the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude sixe times the height thereof.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="method">
                     <head>Another way.</head>
                     <p>If at the first your threed fall on the part 2 of contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie shadow, and at the second on the part one, the space between the 2 standings, shall be sixe time the length or height of the altitude, or the 6 part of that measure shall be the height thereof; and your furthest station shall be distant from the base thereof, twelue times the height thereof.</p>
                     <p>And note that if the scale were diuided vnto 60, 100, or 1000 diuisions, by so much further from the thing to be measured might you find out the height thereof.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="method">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:178591:32"/>
                  <head>How you may likewise by the parts of right shadow in the scale by the ayde of two places finde out any approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able height.</head>
                  <p>PLace your Quadrant handsomly to your eye, til be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the extream of the altitude through the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suall sights, your threed falling on the part 12, and at the middle of your foot make a marke, and going nearer to the base of the altitude directly forward, beholding the extreame or highest part of the altitude, the plummet cutting the part 6, at the middle of your foote make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother marke, double that space, and thereto adioyne the height from your eye to your foote, the summe is the true height of the altitude.</p>
                  <div type="method">
                     <head>Another way.</head>
                     <p>Lift vp your Quadrant as afore, the plummet cutting the part 12, and going nearer till it cut the part 8, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the middle of both your standings, measure that distance, and triple that measure, and thereto adde the height from your eye, you haue the height.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="method">
                     <head>Another way.</head>
                     <p>Let the threed cut the part 12 and 9, marking the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of both your standings, measure the distance, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triple that measure, and adde the height from your eye, you haue the height.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="method">
                     <head>Another way.</head>
                     <p>If at the first station the threed cut the part 12, and at the next station the part 10, sixe times the distance of the 2 station is the height, adding as aforesaid.</p>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:178591:33"/>
                     <p>Or if at the first it fall on the part 12, and at the second on the part 1, then 12 times the distance of the 2 stations is the height desired, adding the height from your eie to the ground.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="rule">
                  <head>A generall rule how you may by a Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Quadrant measure all heights by Arithmeticall skill.</head>
                  <p>NOte what point or diuision of the skale the threed falleth on, your eye beholding through the visual sights of your rule the iust top or extreame part of the altitude, if the threed fall on the parts of right shadow, then multiply the distance from the midle of your foot to the base by 12, and diuide by the parts of the skale wherein the threed fell, adding thereto the height from your eye to the ground, you haue the height. But if the threed fall on the parts of contrarie shadow, then mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply the distance from the middle of your foote to the base by those parts, and diuide by 12, and to the quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient adde the height from your eie to the ground, you haue the altitude likewise.</p>
                  <div type="example">
                     <head>Example.</head>
                     <p>SVppose the plum-line cut the part 5 of contrary sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, the distance from the middle of your foote to the base of the altitude 110 foot, that multiplyed by 5, is 550 foote, the which diuided by 12, yeeldes in the quotient 45 foot ⅚, to which adde fiue foote, the height from your eye to your foote, the summe is fiftie foot ⅚, the true height of that measure.</p>
                     <p>Or suppose the threed fall on the part 6 of right sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:178591:33"/> the distance from the middle of your standing to the base of the Altitude 24 foote, which multiplied by 12 makes 288, diuided by 6, the quotient is 48 foot, to which fiue foote added, the supposed height from your eye to the ground is 53 foote, the height of that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.</p>
                     <p>Note in euery working, whether the ground at your standing be leuell or not with the base of the altitude, if it be either higher or lower than the base, the plum-line falling on the line of leuell, wil tell you what part of the base is leuell with your eye.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="rule">
                  <head>A generall rule to measure the length or distance of the parts or part of any Altitude.</head>
                  <p>You must first finde out the height of either part of the thing you would measure, by the rules afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, in taking the length or height of the top and base of the same, abating the lesse out of the more, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine is your desire. Or setting vp perpendicularly a Gunners Iauelin, Halbard or staffe, diuided into equall parts, a little within the length of the height of the alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude you would measure, mouing your selfe from the same backwards, either lying on your back, or stooping your eye low towards the ground, till you can espie the extreame tops or ends of the altitude and staffe in a streight line from your eie, and then not mouing your eie, view the lowest part of the same thing you would measure, and suppose the visuall line cut or passe by the third part or diuision of the staffe, which imagine to bee diuided into 8 equall parts, or 8 foot the length therof;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:178591:34"/> and that the distance from your eye to the base of the staffe is eighteene foote, and the distance from your eie to the base of the altitude is 120 foot, frame the rule of 3. saying, if eighteene foot the space from your eye to the staffe yeelde 120, foote which is the distance to the base of the altitude, what will 3 foote? multiply 120 by 3, ariseth 360, diuide by 18, the quotient is 20 foote, the height of that part of the altitude you desire to measure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="rule">
                  <head>A rule how by the degrees of the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant by knowing a part or portion of the base or lowest part of any Altitude, to find out the height of the same.</head>
                  <p>GOe so neare to the thing whose height you would measure, setting the rule to your eie, so as the plum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>line falling on the line of leuell, may point equall with the base of the altitude, or else note some marke of the altitudes base, where your visuall sight points at the threed falling on the line of leuell; then raise the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant higher, so standing still as the threed may fall on the first degree thereof, and looking through the sights, marke where the visuall line points at, the distance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene those two markes is to be measured. And lastly, lifting vp your Quadrant, beholding the top thereof through the sights, marke vpon what degree the threed falleth: and so by knowing the distance and height of the first degree, you may easily by the golden rule find out the height of the altitude. Example. Say or suppose the threed falleth on the sixt degree of the quadrant: when you behold the top thereof through the visuall sights, and the knowne distance of one degree is 8 foote, then
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:178591:34"/> say, if on degree yeeld 8 foot, what sixe? you shal haue 48 foote, the true height thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="method">
                  <head>How you may by a Gunners Iauelin or Halbard, or any straight staffe, finde out any approchable height by the shadow.</head>
                  <p>SVppose the Gunners Iauelin be 8 foote in length, fet the same vp perpendicularly, and measure the length of the shadow the same casts, which measure suppose to be twelue foot. Then measure the length of the altitudes shadow, which suppose to be 60 foote. Then framing the rule of Proportion, saying, if 12 foote knowne sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow yeeld 8 foote height, what 60? and so multiplying 60 by 8, and diuiding by 12, the quotient is 40, shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the height of the altitude is iust 40 foot in height; the like rule is in <hi>Vegetios.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="method">
                  <head>Another way without shadow by any streight thing perpendicularly erected to finde out the height of any approch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Altitude.</head>
                  <p>SEt vp a staffe or gunners Iauelin perpendicularly as afore, somewhat within the length of the altitude, going from the same, and lying on your backe, moue your selfe to or from the same, till you can espie the very end of the Iauelin, and the top of the marke in a streight line from your eye: suppose the distance from your eye to the staffe 12 foote, and the distance from your eye to the base of the altitude 60 foote, and the height of the Iauelin 8 foot; say, if twelue foot the space
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:178591:35"/> from your eye to the staffe yeeld 8 foot height, what wil 60 foot (the distance from your eie to the base of the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude?) Multiply and diuide, your quotient is 40, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, shewing the altitude of the thing to be measured. The like rule is in Master <hi>Digs</hi> his Geometricall booke called <hi>Pantometria;</hi> who sheweth also in the same, how by any two staues of equall length ioyned in a right an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle squirewise, you may find any altitude, by setting the one end thereof to your eye, going to or from the thing to be measured, vntill you can by the points or ends of the other staffe with one eye view both the base and top of the altitude, making a mark at the midst of your foot, the distance from that mark to the base is the iust height of the thing you seek to measure.</p>
                  <p>Many mo waies there be to finde out heights, both by the Quadrant, squire, triangle, glasse, staffe, &amp;c. which I let passe: the vnexperienced by these few easie conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions may the sooner attaine the rest.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="method">
                  <head>How you may by the helpe of the Quadrant from any plaine platforme know the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance therefrom to any marke you are to shoote at.</head>
                  <p>LAy your Quadrant flat vpon some stoole, or take a short staffe with a skrew in the end thereof, erecting the same perpendicularly, and put the Quadrant vpon the same skrew; then by the edge of the rule turning the same to the marke whose distance you would measure, or through the visuall sights on the rule espie the marke, and at your standing set vp a Gunners staffe or Iauelin; then turning your body crosse the same, not altering
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:178591:35"/> the rule and Quadrant by the line of leuell, on the edge of the Quadrant espie some other marke athwart the first, and set vp the second staffe, the distance whereof suppose to be 60 foote; then comming to the first stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on where the quadrant is placed, viewing by the edge of the rule through the visuall sights, some other mark in a streight line back from your first station, whose distance suppose 100 feete, and there erect vp the 3 staffe, and so the first and the third staffe will bee in a streight line with the mark, then with a squire or remouing the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant to the 3 station, turning the right angle or line of leuell ouerthwart towards the second station, so as the visuall line may bee parallell to the line that cros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth from the first station to the second, there set vp the 4 staffe, so as the visuall line passing from the same, and running by the second staffe, may crosse the marke or end in a point there with the first visuall line, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance betweene these two last stations suppose 65 feet, the staues thus placed in order abade 60 feete, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance btweene the first and second station from 65 the distance between the 3 and 4 staues, the remaine is 5 for your deuisor; then multiply the said 65 by 100, the
<figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram showing how to measure distance with a quadrant and gunner's staff or javelin</figDesc>
                     </figure>distance from the first to the 3, ariseth 6500, the which diuided by 5, the quotient is 1300 feete, the distance
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:178591:36"/> from the first staffe, to the marke. Behold the figure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, where the cipher O, represents the marke, the vnite 1. your first staffe or station, the figure 2 the second staffe, the figure 3 the third staffe, and the figure 4 the fourth staffe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="method">
                  <head>How you may another way by the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant and your Gunners staffe diuided into euen portions, tell the distance to any marke neare hand that you are to shoote at.</head>
                  <p>SEt the angle of your Quadrant vpon the very point or top of your staffe, the said staffe perpendicularly erected, and through the sights on your ruler espie the marke whose distance you desire to measure, letting a long threed or small line fal to the ground from the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Quadrant whereon the plum line hangs, which threed must be drawne along the line of leuell or edge of the Quadrant to the ground, marking where the threed points at on the ground, beholding the mark through the visuall sights in the rule of the Quadrant: and looke what proportion that part of ground between the staffe and where the threed pointed at, hath to the staffe, the same proportion shall the length to the marke haue to the height or length of the staffe.</p>
                  <div type="example">
                     <head>Example.</head>
                     <p>THe Gunners staffe AB, suppose to bee eight foote long, and the distance betweene the staffe and the ground where the threed points you to (being the space CB) is but 8 inches, therefore looke what proportion CB beareth to the length of the staffe (which reduced
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:178591:36"/> into inches will be 96 inches) the same proportion shall the length to the marke D haue to the staffe, which by the golden rule is thus found. If 8 inches yeeld 96 in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, what will 96 inches? multiply 96 by 96, ariseth 9216 inches, diuided by 8, yeeldes in the quotient 1152 inches, the distance from the staffe to the marke: and note that the higher the pole or staffe is, the further may you measure by this rule; behold the figure.</p>
                     <p>
                        <figure>
                           <figDesc>diagram showing how to measure distance with a quadrant and gunner's staff</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="method">
                  <head>How you may by a Gunners Quadrant readily measure the length of anie wall or curtaine, or the distance betwixt any two markes in the same.</head>
                  <p>GO directly towards one of the said markes, that by supposition you are distant from the same about the length betwixt the two markes whose distance you would measure, laying your Quadrant flat vpon some stoole, or placing the same vpon the skrew of the staffe aforenamed perpendicularly erected, mouing the same to or from the marke you stand against, placing the Quadrant so, as the visuall sight passing from the center of the Quadrant by the line of leuell, may direct you to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:178591:37"/> the said mark, &amp; the visuall line passing from the center of the Quadrant by the 12 point or diuision of the scale which is the hipothemisal line, may direct you to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther marke; and then the length of your standing to the marke which the line of leuell directs you to, is from the same iust the distance betweene the 2 markes you meane to measure. Then looking athwart by the other edge of the Quadrant, or through the sights on your rule, espie some other marke on the ground directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the marke you meane to measure, and the visuall line passing betweene your station and the said marke wil be parallell to the wall or line passing betweene the two markes whose distance you would measure. Then remouing your quadrant before the other marke, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the same so as the line of leuell may direct you to the said marke, and the line passing by your sights on your ruler may direct you to your first station, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance betwixt your two stations being measured, is the iust space betwixt the two markes you seeke to measure, as the demonstration hereunder sheweth, where the
<figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram showing the use of a gunner's quadrant to measure distance</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:178591:37"/> line AB, sheweth the length or distance I would mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure supposed to be 100 paces, and the like number is found both in the line CD, as also in the lines CA and DB, which proues the worke to be truely wrought.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="method">
                  <head>How you may by the former conclusion at one station measure the distance to both the former markes.</head>
                  <p>THe distance from your standing C, to the marke A, which the line of leuell directs you to, is iust 100 paces, that summe squared, makes 1000 paces. The like number of paces is found in the line AB, being multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in it selfe: these two summes beeing ioyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, makes 20000 paces, the quadrant root thereof is 141 paces and almost ½, shewing the true distance from you standing to your furthest marke B.</p>
                  <p>The like order you must obserue to know the iust length of any scaling ladder, to scale the wall of any ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, tower, or towne besieged, in taking the height of the said wall with your quadrant, or otherwise as afore hath beene taught, multiplying that knowne measure in it selfe: and likewise multiplying the distance from the foote of the ladder (or the space betweene the base of the wall and that part of ground where the foote of the ladder stands) in it selfe, adding those two summes together, extracting the square root thereof, your quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient wil tell you the length of your scaling ladder. Or by knowing the length of your scaling ladder and the height of the wall, multiplying euery number in it selfe as aforesaid, abating the lesser summe from the greater, the Quadrant roote of the remaine is the distance of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:178591:38"/> the ground from the foote of the ladder to the base of the wal. Or by knowing the length of the scaling ladder and the length of the ground from the foote of the lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the base of the wall, you may find out the height of the wall, in multiplying each number in it selfe, aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the lesser summe out of the greater, extracting the square roote of the remaine, the quotient will answer your demand, as is demonstrated and proued in the 47 proposition of the first booke of <hi>Euclids Elements.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="method">
                  <head>How you may by the ayde of two staues or Gunners Iauelins perpendicularly erected, by knowing the distance from your standing to the middle part betwixt any two markes, measure the distance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the said markes.</head>
                  <p>ADmit the line AB is the 2 markes whose distance I would measure, and the line CD is the knowne measure to the middle part betwixt the said markes, which I suppose to be 200 feete, erect vp the two staues EF, so as the visuall line from your eye at C, passing by the staues, may point directly to the said markes AB.
<figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram showing the use of two perpendicular staves or gunner's javelins to measure distance</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:178591:38"/> The distance betwixt the two staues suppose to bee 20 feete, and the distance from your eye to the staues 24 feet; frame the rule of 3, saying, if 24 foot (being the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance from your eye to the staues) yeeld 20 foot (which is the space betwixt either staffe) what will 200 foote (which is the length of the line from C to D?) Multiply 200 by 20, ariseth 4000, diuide by 24, the quotient is 166 feete ⅔, the true distance betwixt the two markes AB which you seeke to measure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="method">
                  <head>How you may by the diuisions of the scale of your quadrant, by knowing the distance to any tower, steeple, tree, or other mark, not farre distant, know how much the same is higher or lower than your standing.</head>
                  <p>THe distance known, note by what point of the scale of your quadrant the index or threed fals on, in viewing the same marke through the sights on your ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, by which point or diuision you must diuide 12, (the diuisions of your scale). and note what comes in your quotient, by which quotient number diuide the distance from your standing to the base of the marke, your new quotient number will tell you how much the top of the marke or altitude is higher than your eye.</p>
                  <div type="example">
                     <head>Example.</head>
                     <p>THe distance from my standing to the base of the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude suppose to be 200 feete, the plumline falling on the part 6 of contrarie shadow, I diuide 12 by 6, the quotient is 2, by which quotient number I diuide 200 feet (the space betwixt my standing and the marke, and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:178591:39"/> so I find 100 in my new quotient: so I affirm the top of the marke was 100 foot higher than my eye. The like is to be done for descents in turning the contrary angle of the quadrant to your eye.</p>
                     <p>Note that to take the distance betweene any 2 markes with the quadrant, the markes beeing not farre asunder, you must obserue the like order you doe in taking heights, sauing that in measuring heights the quadrant must euer hang so as the plummet and threed hauing libertie to moue to and fro, may euer hang perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly: and to take distances the quadrant must euer lye flat, so as the same doe euer make a square angle against the markes whose distances you would measure: in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king whereof an <hi>Athilleda,</hi> index, or pointer (as some terme it) placed in the center or angle of the quadrant hauing two sights thereon, will direct you much better to the markes than the threed. Many other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusions are to be found out, and wrought by this instrument: to the inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious these few may suffice.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:178591:39"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>